Dr. rer. nat. Julian Q. Kosciessa

Thomas van Aquinostraat 4, Nijmegen julian.kosciessa@donders.ru.nl

ORCID: 0000-0002-4553-2794











I am a postdoctoral researcher working at the intersection of cognitive, computational and systems neurosciences. My work aims to improve the characterization of neural dynamics, and clarify the functional role of neural rhythms and noise in flexible cognition. My experimental research combines neuroscientific techniques, and extends available methods via scientific open source software development.















simulations

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Researcher

2022 - PRESENT

Donders Institute for Brain, Cognition and Behaviour Nijmegen, Netherlands

Predoctoral Research Fellow

2016 - 2020

IMPRS Comp2Psych Max Planck UCL Center for Computational Psychiatry and Aging Berlin, Germany

Research Assistant/Intern

2010 - 2016

Berlin, Germany London, UK Singapore, Singapore

EDUCATION

Humboldt Universität zu Berlin

2016 - 2020

Psychology

Dr. rer. nat. (summa cum laude)

Humboldt Universität zu Berlin

2014 - 2016

Mind & Brain - Track Brain M.Sc. Master of Science

Freie Universität Berlin

2011 - 2014

Psychology

B.Sc. Bachelor of Science

SKILLS

MATLAB R

UNIX



Pvthon Git Mandarin ____

KEY PUBLICATIONS



Kosciessa, J. Q., Lindenberger, U., & Garrett, D. D. (2021)

وروري والمطاقة والمتعرب والمرابط والمرز والمرز والمرز والمرز والمرابط والمرابط والمرابط والمرابط والمتعرب والمرابط والمتعرب والمت

Thalamocortical excitability adjustments guide human perception under uncertainty **Nature Communications**



Kosciessa, J. Q., Kloosterman, N. A., & Garrett, D. D. (2020)

Standard multiscale entropy reflects neural dynamics at mismatched temporal scales: What's signal irregularity got to do with it? **PLoS Computational Biology**



Kosciessa, J. Q., Grandy, T. H., Garrett, D. D., & Werkle-Bergner, M. (2020) Single-trial characterization of neural rhythms: Potential and challenges. Neurolmage

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

09/2022 - PRESENT Postdoctoral Researcher / Radboud Excellence Fellow

> Donders Institute for Brain, Cognition and Behaviour Radboud University, Nijmegen, The Netherlands

PI: Dr. Lennart Verhagen

07/2020 - 07/2022 **Postdoctoral Researcher**

Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin, Germany

10/2016 - 03/2020 Predoctoral Research Fellow (IMPRS COMP2PSYCH)

> Max Planck UCL Center for Computational Psychiatry and Aging Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin, Germany Supervisors: Prof. Dr. Ulman Lindenberger, Dr. Douglas D. Garrett

10/2015 - 03/2016 Research Intern

> UCL Institute of Cognitive Neuroscience PIs: Prof. Emrah Düzel & Prof. Ray Dolan

PI: Dr. Dorothea Hämmerer

03/2015 - 07/2015 Research Intern

Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin, Germany

Center for Adaptive Rationality (ARC)

PI: Dr. Wouter van den Bos

09/2012 - 09/2013 Research Assistant

07/2014 - 09/2015 Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin, Germany 04/2016 - 09/2016 Cognitive and neuronal dynamics of memory across the lifespan

Pls: Dr. Markus Werkle-Bergner & Dr. Yee Lee Shing

01/2014 - 05/2014 Research Intern

Cognitive Neuroscience Laboratory, Duke-NUS, Singapore

PI: Prof. Michael Chee

Supervisor: Dr. Irma Kurniawan

EDUCATION

10/2016 - 10/2020 Humboldt Universität zu Berlin

Psychology. Dr. rer. nat. (summa cum laude)

10/2014 - 09/2016 Humboldt Universität zu Berlin

Mind & Brain – Track Brain. M.Sc. Master of Science (GPA: 1.0)

09/2015 - 04/2016 **University College London**

Two Erasmus exchange terms. Institute of Neurology

07/2013 - 05/2014 National University of Singapore (NUS)

Two exchange semesters. Faculty of Arts and Social Sciences

10/2011 - 09/2014 Freie Universität Berlin

Psychology. B.Sc. Bachelor of Science (GPA: 1.1)

TEACHING & TALKS (SELECTED)

2022: Workshop:

Reusable data management with DataLad Cognitive Psychology. University of Munster. Germany

2022: Invited Research Talks:

Dynamic neural regimes for flexible decisions under uncertainty

- Translational Decision-Making Seminar

[Virtual: University of Minnesota/Université de Montréal]

- Biopsychology. University of Munster. Germany
- Donders Institute for Brain, Cognition and Behaviour
- 2022: Invited Symposium Talk:

Influences of arousal and cortical excitability on adaptive perceptual decision making. International Conference of Cognitive Neuroscience. Helsinki, Finland

2021: Research Talk:

The role of neural dynamics in flexible perception under uncertainty. Computational Neuroscience Symposium. Osnabrück, Germany

2021: Invited Research Talks:

Thalamocortical excitability adjustments guide human perception under uncertainty.

- Shine Lab, University of Sydney, Australia
- Halassa Lab, Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT), U.S.A.
- 2020: Invited Collogium Talk:

Measurement and relevance of rhythmic and aperiodic human brain dynamics. Biopsychology und Neuroergonomics Lab. Technical University. Berlin, Germany

2020: Invited Workshop:

Multi-scale entropy as a tool to characterize neural signal irregularity. EEG Meeting. Max Planck Institute for Human Development. Berlin, Germany

2018: Invited Seminar:

Methods for the analysis of rhythmic and arrhythmic brain activity. International Max Planck Research School on the Life Course. Berlin, Germany

FUNDING & AWARDS

- 2022: Radboud Excellence Fellowship (200.000 EUR)
- 2022: Otto Hahn Medal of the Max Planck Society (7.500 EUR)
- 2022: DAAD Conference Travel Grant: International Conference of Cognitive Neuroscience
- 2021: DGPA Brain Products Young Scientist Award 2021
- 2021: DAAD Conference Travel Grant to OHBM Meeting 2021
- 2021: Merit Abstract Award OHBM Meeting 2021
- 2018: IBRO Poster Award Interpreting BOLD 2018
- 2018: DAAD Conference Travel Grant to Interpreting BOLD 2018 (Oxford, UK)
- 2015/2016: DAAD Erasmus Stipend (University College London, UK)
- 2014: DAAD PROMOS Stipend (National University Singapore, Singapore)

SUPERVISION

2021/22: MSc Claire Pleche

M.Sc. Student in Cognitive Neuroscience, Ecole Normale Supérieure de Paris, France Probing the role of neural variability in flexible decision-making under uncertainty co-supervision with Dr. Douglas D. Garrett

2021: Mentor at Neuromatch Academy

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITES

- Ad-hoc peer reviewer: PNAS, PLoS Biology, NeuroImage (9x), Journal of Neuroscience, Psychophysiology, Brain Topography, European Journal of Neuroscience, Mindfulness, PLoS One
- Member of the Organization for Human Brain Mapping (OHBM)
- Associate Member of the Deutsche Gesellschaft für Psychology (DGPs)
- Member of the International Neuroinformatics Coordinating Facility (INCF)